foreign
[Music]
compounds measured in the bloodstream of
thousands of individuals the one most
associated with the lowest rates of
disease and death was
ergothionine higher blood levels were
associated with low risk of heart
disease stroke and death from all causes
put together over a period of more than
20 years
ergothionine is an unusual amino acid
although it was discovered more than a
century ago it was ignored until
recently when researchers found that
humans have a highly specific transport
of protein in our body specifically
designed to pull Ergo thinning out of
food and into body tissue it's even
upregulated right before meal times this
suggests that ergothian plays an
important physiological role but what
our first clue was the tissue
distribution ergothanine concentrates in
parts of your body where there's lots of
free radicals the lens of your eye or
liver for example as well as sensitive
tissues such as bone marrow and semen
researchers found it acts as a
cytoprotected a cell protector depriving
human cells of virgothionine leads to
accelerated DNA damage and cell death
because we can only get it in food and
there's toxicity associated with its
depletion Johns Hopkins University
researchers conclude that ergothionine
may represent a new vitamin if it were
classified as such that would make it
the first new vitamin since the last new
vitamin B12 was isolated back in 1948.
however traditional vitamins are
characterized by the manifestation of an
overt dietary deficiency disease within
a short time frame and no specific
deficiency disease has yet been
identified but perhaps deficiency
diseases are staring Us in the face low
blood levels of vertical thymine are
correlated with increased risk of
Frailty cardiovascular disease cognitive
impairment dementia and Parkinson's
disease to describe nutrients they may
not necessarily be essential for life
but may be essential for long-term
Health the famous biochemist Bruce Ames
coined the term longevity vitamin and
identified ergothionine as a punitive
candidate one of the best dietary
sources it's not made by plants or
animals only fungi like mushrooms and
certain soil bacteria plants can suck
some up from the soil and animals who
eat the plants can similarly benefit but
the highest Levels by far have been
reported in mushrooms
excessive tillage of the soil which is a
common practice in modern agriculture
can disrupt the mysegal network the
fungi filaments that pass ergothionine
along to the roots of crops leaving
mushrooms in Tempeh fungi fermented
soybean cake as the only concentrated
dietary sources this is on a dry weight
basis though and mushrooms are like 90
water so if you change this to a
prepared wet weight tempeh does even
better on more of a per serving basis as
mushrooms go shiitake may have
comparable levels to oyster mushrooms
about five times more than white button
mushrooms but may also be five times as
expensive unless you grow your own
oyster mushrooms can be grown in less
than two weeks with Just Add Water kits
here's a pick from my own personal stash
puccinis may lead the pack though which
could explain why Italians average more
than four times the average herbal
thymine intake of Americans but even
just eating a cup a day of plain white
button mushrooms can double or go
finding concentrations in the blood
yes ergothionine is associated with
reduced mortality but it was also the
blood metabolite most strongly connected
to a health-conscious food pattern so it
could just have been a proxy for
healthier eating and look correlation
doesn't mean causation instead of low
ergothian levels leading to disease
maybe disease somehow leads to lower
ergothionine levels what evidence do we
have that we should go out of our way to
eat mushrooms well mushrooms can reduce
atherosclerosis and butter fat-fed mice
and fruit flies fed a one percent oyster
mushroom diet did show a slight but
significant survival advantage and we
suspect it's the ergothionine since you
can give it straight and still get a
life extension effect but what evidence
do we have in people well mushroom
consumption is associated with lower
risk of cancer driven mainly by lower
breast cancer rates and mushroom
consumption is associated with a low
risk of dying prematurely from all
causes put together I have covered
Interventional trials showing for
example that even just a few mushrooms a
day can improve immune function but
ergothinine may be an under recognized
dietary micronutrient for healthy Aging
in other ways as well
dietary ergothionine is known to cross
the blood-brain barrier since can be
found in human cerebral spinal fluid and
postmortem brain samples perhaps this is
why I study in Singapore found that
those who consume more than two servings
of mushrooms a week had less than half
the odds of suffering from mild
cognitive impairment compared to less
than once a week and a study more than
10 000 Japanese Elders found that three
or more times a week mushroom eaters had
a significantly lower risk of developing
dementia over a period of about six
years
with cross-sectional studies correlating
mushroom consumption with better brain
function researchers decided to put it
to the test using Lion's main mushroom
which is especially popular in
traditional Chinese medicine
randomized double blind
placebo-controlled trials on people with
normal cognitive function on people with
mild cognitive impairment and on those
with early stage Alzheimer's disease did
find small cognitive or functional
improvements after months of a third to
a full teaspoon of powdered lion's mane
mushroom a day compared to placebo
interestingly blood ergothian levels
appear to decline after about age 60 and
this decline is tied to both cognitive
decline and Frailty
and this does not appear to be due to
declining mushroom intake with age so
perhaps the function of the ergothian
transporter at the blood-brain barrier
declines with age potentially making
mushroom intake all the more beneficial
as we grow older
so if I was to create a Dr greger's
Baker's Dozen I would probably add
mushrooms to the list
[Music]
thank you